U.S. President's Railroad Commission Photographs 5003 P
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
U.S. President's Railroad Commission Photographs
1960-1961
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
U.S. President's Railroad Commission
Anderson, Donald H.
Anderson, Leo R.
Bartley, Edward J.
DuBose, L. A.
Dunn, Walter R.
Franklin, Henry H.
Golden, James L., Jr.
Guinea, Edgar R.
Guthrie, Clifton
Harp, Autry A.
Howell, Fred D.
LaRue, M. H.
Mahoney, Barney J.
Neupert, Raymond A.
Pippy, Herman D.
Plock, Henry G.
Redmond, James B.
Ritchie, Joseph H.
Shimel, Walter
Spencer, Harold
Stanley, Roy T.
Stemrich, James
Strommen, Arnold M.
Vawter, Howard M.
Vick, Simeon G.
Vickers, Sanford
Whitworth, T. A.
Zumwikle, V. S.
5003 P
4.5 cubic feet
4.5 linear ft.
Photographs.
Photographs of railroad workers, yards, trains, buildings, hearings and cardboard exhibit materials.
8166035
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Elizabeth Parker, September 11, 2013
EAD encoding:
Elizabeth Parker, December 05, 2017
Biographical / Historical
The U.S. Presidential Railroad Commission was established by Executive Order No. 10891 of November 1, 1960, to consider a controversy between carriers represented by the Eastern, Western, and Southeastern Carriers' Conference Committees and the Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers, the Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen, the Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen, the Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen, and the Switchmen's Union of North America.
Specifically, the controversy surrounded the assertion by the carriers that firemen were not needed on diesel locomotives and that their positions should be eliminated. The unions, on the other hand, maintained that modern diesel locomotives were much too complex to be operated by one engineer and that firemen were necessary to ensure safety. Seventy-nine witnesses appeared before the Commission and statements were filed on behalf of one hundred and fifty-five additional witnesses.
On February 28, 1962, the Commission filed its final report, recommending substantial changes in many of the railroad's work rules. It agreed with the carriers' position that 40,000 firemen helpers who served on freight trains were no longer needed. It also recommended that the railroads "should have an unlimited right to technological change."
See Cornell University Library's catalog entry for the final Report here.
Scope and Contents
Inclusive date range: 1960-1962
Bulk dates: 1960
This collection consists of 1,656 images (8 film negatives and 1,648 photographs) that were taken on behalf of the railroad labor organizations to support the testimony of their members before the U.S. President's Railroad Commission regarding the crew consist dispute and their assertions regarding the necessity of the fireman position.
The railroad labor unions asked their members who worked for various carriers across the country to document their workplaces, such as train yards, stations and terminals, railroad tracks in urban and rural settings, industry sidings, industrial facilities, and locomotive engines. These photographs document the railroad facilities and equipment of 48 carriers across the United States, and were taken by more than 30 railroad employees, the majority of whom were employed as firemen and engineers.
A number of the photographs were entered into evidence by the unions, but not all of them were used in evidentiary proceedings before the Commission. Both evidentiary photographs and those not used in the proceedings are located in this collection.
The photographs are arranged into 34 Series. The series each contain photographs documenting a specific carrier in a unique location, taken by an employee or employees of that carrier on behalf of their union. Where possible, the photographs have been identifed by their exhibit number as referred to in testimony or, where that is lacking, internal numbering written on the versos of the photographs. Descriptions of the images are taken from the testimony of the photographers. For those photographs that were not included as exhibits, descriptions have been assembled from contemporaneous notes, geographical clues found in the images, and other information found in other exhibits submitted by the Organizations to the Commision.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5003: U.S. President's Railroad Commission Records 5003 MB: U.S. President's Railroad Commission Memorabilia 6040 P: Railroad Collection Photographs
Arrangement
Series I: Birmingham Southern Railroad: Industries and Yards
Series II: Boston and Maine Railroad (B&M): Boston Terminal Yards
Series III: Baltimore and Ohio Railroad (B&O): Chicago Division
Series IV: Central Railroad of New Jersey: Buttonwood Yards and Wilkes-Barre Interchange
Series V: Chicago & North Western Railway: Chicago Terminal Division, Proviso Yards
Series VI: Chicago River and Indiana Railroad: Chicago Industries and Union Stock Yards
Series VII: Denver's Burnham Yards: The Rio Grande (DRGW), Colorado & Southern, and Santa Fe Railway (ATSF) facilities
Series VIII: Duluth, Missabe and Iron Range Railway: mining and shipping operations
Series IX: Great Northern Railway: Everett and Seattle, Washington
Series X: Great Northern Railway: Minneapolis Junction
Series XI: Illinois Central Railroad: Memphis Division
Series XII: Chicago, Rock Island and Pacific Railroad: Missouri/Kansas Division, Kansas City Terminal and Yards
Series XIII: Long Island Railroad (LIRR): Car Float operations at Long Island City and Hudson River Railyards
Series XIV: Louisville and Nashville Railroad (L&N): Birmingham Division, yards, passenger terminals, and industries
Series XV: Chicago, Milwaukee, St. Paul and Pacific Railroad (The Milwaukee Road): locomotives and rolling stock
Series XVI: New York Central Railroad (NYCRR) Cleveland Division Collinwood Yards
Series XVII: Northern Pacific Railroad and Great Northern Railway: facilities in Spokane, Washington
Series XVIII: Norfolk and Western Railroad: Norfolk Terminal and Yards
Series XIX: New York, New Haven and Hartford Railroad: Yards and Tracks from New York City to Boston, Massachusetts
Series XX: U.S. President's Railroad Commission
Series XXI: Pennsylvania Railroad: Enola Yards, Rutherford Yards, Harrisburg Penn Station
Series XXII: Pennsylvania Railroad: Philadelphia Division
Series XXIII: Reading Railroad: Rutherford Yards and Steelton Industries
Series XXIV: Southern Railway: Inman Yards and Atlanta Terminal
Series XXV: Southern Pacific Railroad: Los Angeles SoPac Yards
Series XXVI: Southern Pacific Railroad: Western Division, West Oakland Yards
Series XXVII: Southern Pacific Railroad: Pacific Division, El Paso Yards
Series XXVIII: Southern Pacific Railroad: Brooklyn Yards (Portland, Oregon)
Series XXIX: Southern Pacific Railroad: Coast Division, San Francisco
Series XXX: Texas and Pacific Railway: El Paso Yards
Series XXXI: Terminal Railroad Association of St. Louis: St. Louis Union Station and surrounding yards
Series XXXII: Union Pacific Railroad: Denver Union Terminal and Freight Houses
Series XXXIII: Union Pacific Railroad: Pocatello, Idaho passenger depot and freight yards
Series XXXIV: Washington Terminal Co. Railroad: Washington D.C. Union Station and Potomac Yards
Wood Street Yards -- Illinois -- Chicago; Bridges; Industries; Mines and mineral resources; Locomotive engineers; Locomotive firemen; Locomotives; Railroad cars; Railroad crossings; Railroad passenger cars; Railroad stations; Railroad stations -- California; Railroad stations -- Alabama; Railroad stations -- Texas; Railroad stations -- Washington; Railroad stations -- Georgia; Railroad stations -- Connecticut; Railroad stations -- Massachusetts; Railroad stations -- Oregon; Railroad stations -- Missouri; Railroad stations -- Colorado; Railroad stations -- New Jersey; Railroad stations -- New York state; Railroad stations -- Illinois; Railroad stations -- Pennsylvania; Railroad stations -- District of Columbia; Railroad stations -- Kansas; Railroad stations -- Virginia; Railroad stations -- Tennessee; Railroad stations -- Minnesota; Railroad stations -- Idaho; Railroad switches; Railroad terminals; Railroad tracks; Railroad yards; Railroads -- Buildings and structures; Railroads -- Employees; Railroads -- Equipment and supplies; Railroads -- Freight; Railroads -- Maintenance and repair; Railroads -- Signaling; Shipping; Steamboats; Tugboats; Atchison, Topeka, and Santa Fe Railway Company; Atlantic Coast Line Railroad Company; Baltimore and Ohio Chicago Terminal Railroad Company; Baltimore and Ohio Railroad Company; Birmingham Southern Railroad Company; Boston and Maine Railroad; Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers (U.S.) (BLE); Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen (BLFandE); Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen (BRT); Central of Georgia Railway; Central Railroad of New Jersey; Chicago and North Western Transportation Company; Chicago Great Western Railway Company (1892-1909); Chicago River and Indiana Railroad Company; Chicago, Burlington and Quincy Railroad Company; Chicago, Milwaukee, St. Paul, and Pacific Railroad Company; Chicago, Rock Island, and Pacific Railroad Company (1866-1880); Colorado and Southern Railway; Delaware and Hudson Railway Company; Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad Company; Denver and Rio Grande Western Railroad Company; Duluth, Missabe, and Iron Range Railway; Erie Railroad Company; Erie-Lackawanna Railroad Company; Express Service; Florida East Coast Railway; Great Northern Railway Company (U.S.); Illinois Central Railroad Company; Kansas City Terminal Railway; Lehigh Valley Railroad Company; Long Island Rail Road; Louisville and Nashville Railroad Company; Minneapolis, St. Paul and Sault Ste. Marie Railway Company; Missouri Pacific Railroad Company; New York Central Railroad Company; New York, Chicago and St. Louis Railroad; New York, New Haven, and Hartford Railroad Company; Norfolk and Portsmouth Belt Line Railroad Company; Norfolk and Western Railway; Northern Pacific Railroad Company610; Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen (ORC); Pacific Coast Railroad Company; Panhandle and Santa Fe Railway Company; President's Railroad Commission (U.S.); Reading Company; Seaboard Air Line Railway Company. Virginia Division; Southern Pacific Railroad Company; Southern Railway (U.S.); Spokane, Portland, and Seattle Railway; St. Louis Terminal Railroad Association; St. Louis-San Francisco Railway Company; Switchmen's Union of North America (SUNA); Terminal Railroad Association of St. Louis; Texas & Pacific Railway; Union Pacific Railroad Company; Virginian Railway; Wabash Railroad; Washington Terminal Company; Western Maryland Railway Company; Western Pacific Railroad Company; 30th Street Yard -- Alabama -- Birmingham; 7th Street Terminal -- California -- San Francisco; Alfalfa Yard -- Texas -- El Paso; Argo Yard -- Washington -- Seattle; Atlanta Terminal Station -- Georgia -- Atlanta; Atlanta Union Station -- Georgia -- Atlanta; Bayshore Yard -- California -- San Francisco; Bayside Yard -- Washington -- Everett; Belle Dock Yard -- Connecticut -- New Haven; Bessemer Yard -- Alabama -- Bessemer; Birmingham Terminal Station-- Alabama -- Birmingham; Boston Terminal Yards -- Massachusetts -- Cambridge; Boyles Yard -- Alabama -- Birmingham; Bridgeport Yards -- Connecticut -- Bridgeport; Brooklyn Yards -- Oregon -- Portland; Burlington Railroad Yard -- Missouri -- St. Joseph; Burnham Yards -- Colorado -- Denver; Butte Street Yard -- California -- Los Angeles; Buttonwood Yards -- New Jersey -- Hanover Township; Cedar Hill Yard -- Connecticut -- New Haven; Chicago and North Western Passenger Terminal -- Illinois -- Chicago; Clarksdale Station -- Missouri -- Clarksdale; Collinwood Yard -- Ohio -- Cleveland; Delaware Avenue-- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia; Denver Union Station -- Colorado -- Denver; East Bridgeport Yard -- Connecticut -- East Bridgeport; East Thomas Yard -- Alabama -- Birmingham; Elmhurst Depot -- Illinois -- Elmhurst; Enola Yards -- Pennsylvania -- Harrisburg; Ensley Yard-- Alabama -- Birmingham; Everett Passenger Depot -- Washington -- Everett; Fairhill Yard -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia; First Street Yard -- Massachusetts -- Boston; Girard Point Yard -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia; Grand Central Terminal -- New York State -- New York; Gray's Ferry Yard -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia; Great Northern Depot -- Washington -- Spokane; Guild's Lake Yard -- Oregon -- Portland; Halstead Street Yard -- Illinois -- Chicago; Harlem River Yard -- New York -- New York State; Harrisburg Penn Station -- Pennsylvania -- Harrisburg; Harrisburg Yards -- Pennsylvania -- Harrisburg; Hudson Rail Yards -- New York -- New York State; Inman Yards -- Georgia -- Atlanta; Interbay Yard -- Washington -- Seattle; Ivy City Car Shop -- District of Columbia -- Washington; Kansas City Terminal -- Missouri -- Kansas City; Kansas City Terminal Yards -- Kansas -- Kansas City; Kansas City Union Station -- Missouri -- Kansas City; King Street Station -- Washington -- Seattle; Lambert's Point Yard -- Norfolk, VA; Lincoln Street Terminal -- Illinois -- Chicago; Melrose Park Depot -- Illinois -- Melrose Park; Memphis Terminal Yard -- Tennessee -- Memphis; Midvale Yard -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia; Minneapolis Junction -- Minnesota -- Minneapolis; Mission Bay Yards -- California -- San Francisco; New Haven Union Station -- Connecticut -- New Haven; Oak Park Depot -- Illinois -- Oak Park; Oakland Yard -- California -- Oakland; Penn Coach Yard -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia; Pocatello Passenger Depot -- Idaho -- Pocatello; Pocatello Yards -- Idaho -- Pocatello; Portland Union Station -- Oregon -- Portland; Portland Union Station Yard --- Oregon -- Portland; Portlock Yard -- Virginia -- Norfolk; Potomac Yards --Virginia -- Alexandria; Proviso Yards -- Illinois -- Chicago; River Street Yard -- Connecticut -- New Haven; Rutherford Yards -- Pennsylvania -- Harrisburg; Seaboard Yard -- Alabama -- Birmingham; Seattle House Yard -- Washington -- Seattle; Sewell's Point Yard -- Virginia -- Norfolk; Southern Pacific Yards -- California -- Los Angeles; Stamford Passenger and Freight Y-- Texas -- El Paso; Tidewater Yard -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia; Topeka Terminal -- Kansas --Topeka; U.S. Army Base -- New York State -- Bay Ridge; Union Station -- Missouri -- St. Louis; Union Stock Yardsds -- Illinois -- Chicago; Union Yard -- Minnesota -- Minneapolis; Uptown Yard -- Texas -- El Paso; Washington DC Union Station -- District of Columbia -- Washington; Water Street Yard -- Connecticut -- New Haven; West Oakland Diesel Shop -- California -- Oakland; Wilkes Barre Yards -- Wilkes Barre, PA
8166035
- Series I: Birmingham Southern Railroad: Industries and Yards
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of photographs of the Birmingham Southern Railroad, which were submitted to the Commission as Employees' Exhibit 36, are referred to by the letter I in testimony, and were taken by James L. Golden, Jr. Mr. Golden worked as a fireman and engineer for Birmingham Southern and was the general chairman of the local BLF&E. The Birmingham Southern Railroad was a subsidiary of the U.S. Steel Corporation. It was a terminal switching and road haul carrier, operating a main line between Birmingham and Bessemer, Alabama. The photographs in this series depict the various industries served by this carrier as well as the train yards in Ensley and Birmingham, Alabama.
  - Break-up and Classification Yard, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 2)
    This yard is located south of the steel mills seen in photo, and north of 34th Street. There are 28 classifications tracks on the west side (to left of photo), and 4 leads from the main line on the east side of the yard. This is a kick yard. The building to the right is the yard office. Crews report for duty at the yard office and cross over to pick up their engines. The yard is also an interchange with Southern, L&N, and SLSF railroads.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 2)
  - Trackage of the Tennessee Coal and Iron Railroad Co, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 3)
    Located just south of U.S. Steel works at Ensley. BS has trackage rights and delivers cars to TC&I Railroad at Pratt Railroad Yard (just south of photo's location). The tracks in the photo run north and south. The TC&I hauls hot metal while the BS hauls coal and ore. Close clearance between tracks requires extra vigilance from engineer and fireman. Note cross walks and road way next to and crossing tracks.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 3)
  - Five Unit Road Freight Train Moving into Yard, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 4)
    The tracks run north and south. The five unit diesel is on the inbound main line; to the left of the units is the outbound main line. This is a hump yard; crews work from both ends of the yard. The yard is always congested with yard and road crews from various railroads. Interchanges and deliveries between BS, the SL&SF, the IC, and Central of Georgia Railroads occur in this facility.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 4)
  - Five Unit Road Freight Train Moving into Yard, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 5)
    Same movement as in photo I-3; shows progress of train into yard.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 5)
  - Five Unit Road Freight Train Moving into Yard, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 6)
    Same movement as in photo I-3; shows progress of train and "S" curve train makes going into the yard.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 6)
  - Steel Industry Industrial Siding, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 7)
    Industry is U.S. Pipe Shop.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 7)
- Series II: Boston and Maine Railroad (B&M): Boston Terminal Yards
  This series consists of photographs of the B&M Railroad's facilities in Boston, Massachusetts. These photographs were submitted to the Commission as Employees' Exhibit 21, are referred to by the letter C in testimony, and were taken by Walter P. Dunn. Mr. Dunn was employed as an engineman in the B&M's switching operations in the Boston Terminal Yards. The B&M was a class I railroad operating in northern New England, offering both passenger and freight service. The photographs document the switching operations performed by the B&M in freight yards located in north Boston and Cambridge, Massachusetts.
  - Mystic Wharf Yard, Charlestown, Boston Terminal, 1960 (Box 53, Folder 21)
    Heavily traveled crossing over which all switching is done. The truck is crossing the tracks even though a train is approaching from the upper yards.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 53, Folder 21)
  - Yard 7, Unprotected Crossing, Lechmere Square, Cambridge, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 8)
    Yard 7 (North Station) Water Street crossing, looking west. Fireman observes crossing and other safety features. Crossing is inside the switching yard.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 8)
  - Yard 7 and Yard 4, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 9)
    Piggybacking in center-left of frame. Track curvature to left and right. Overhead bridge, no personnel on top of cars allowed. Cannot ride on side of car. Tracks at right of at picture used by workers as exit from A House.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 9)
  - Yard 7, Unprotected Crossing, Lechmere Square, Cambridge, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 10)
    A House and B House tracks. Yard office in center of photo, behind semi-truck crossing tracks on Water Street.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 10)
  - Yard 7, Unprotected Crossing, Lechmere Square, Cambridge, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 11)
    A and B House tracks. Engines work headed west. Most tracks have left and right curvature with unprotected crossing on left side of engine. Yard office in center of picture, behind Water Street crossing.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 11)
  - Yard 7, Unprotected Crossing, Lechmere Square, Cambridge, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 12)
    A House and B House tracks. Yard office in center of photo behind Water Street crossing.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 12)
  - Yard 7, Unprotected Crossing, Lechmere Square, Cambridge, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 13)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 13)
  - Yard 7, Lechmere Square, Cambridge, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 14)
    Looking East. Ground crew at west end with cars. Fireman observing crossing and unknown factors in easterly direction. Piggyback trailer on car being moved by B&M Unit #1209
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 14)
  - "A" House Platforms, Yard 7, Lechmere Square, Cambridge, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 15)
    Curvature to left and right. Note low clearance above and to the side. Platforms and dollies fouling platform on fireman's side.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 15)
  - Yard 7, Lechmere Square, Cambridge, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 16)
    Looking East. B&M Unit #1209 no longer has piggyback trailer.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 16)
  - Yard 7 "The Hole" Lechmere Square, Cambridge, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 17)
    Looking out into yard from freight house. Unprotected crossing heavily traveled by crews after piggybacks are delivered and dispatched. Clearance makes working on top of or on the sides of cars impossible. All work here performed through motions to man on left side of engine.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 17)
  - Yard 7, Second Section, "A" House, Lechmere Square, Cambridge, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 18)
    Looking west, back of Yard Office in center of picture.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 18)
  - "A" House Platforms, Yard 7, Lechmere Square, Cambridge, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 19)
    Curvature to left, no clearance on top or on sides of cars. Note platforms between cars. Work performed on right side of engine, which depends on the fireman to protect on left side for workmen safety.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 19)
  - "A" House Platforms, Yard 7, Lechmere Square, Cambridge, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 20)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 20)
  - "A" House Platforms, Yard 7, Lechmere Square, Cambridge, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 21)
    Looking east. Curvature to left, no clearance on top or on sides of cars. Work performed on right side of engine, which depends on the fireman to protect on left side for workmen safety.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 21)
  - "A" House Platforms, Yard 7, Lechmere Square, Cambridge, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 22)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 22)
  - Yard 7, Unprotected Crossing, Lechmere Square, Cambridge, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 23)
    Eastward curvature, tracks crossover. Gates in front of crossing in "Up" position. Second unprotected crossing in front of yard office.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 23)
  - Yard 7, Unprotected Crossing, Lechmere Square, Cambridge, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 24)
    Eastward curvature, tracks crossover. Gates in front of Water Street crossing in "Up" position. Second unprotected crossing in front of yard office.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 24)
  - Yard 7 "C" House, Lechmere Square, Cambridge, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 25)
    "C" House tracks. Left and right curvature. No clearance on top of or on sides of cars. Work by ground crews done on both sides of engine. Crossing flagged during daylight hours. No protection at night. Heavy traffic day and night.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 25)
  - Yard 7 "C" House, Lechmere Square, Cambridge, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 26)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 26)